<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Antidote against the present fears and jealousies of the nation by an impartial hand.</title>
            <author>Impartial hand.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23120</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12063361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12063361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53321</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53321)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 49:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Antidote against the present fears and jealousies of the nation by an impartial hand.</title>
                  <author>Impartial hand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.E. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53321:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST THE PRESENT FEARS AND JEALOUSIES OF THE NATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By an Impartial Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With Approbation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> at the Seven Stars in <hi>Ave-Mary-Lane,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53321:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53321:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANTIDOTE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen I conſider the preſent Condition of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſeditious endeavours of our Enemies of all ſorts, the ſlanderous Reports in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and the ſtrange Jealouſies which men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and wicked deſigns foment, to the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting of our minds, and to the prejudice of the Religious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted Intentions of a moſt Gracious King, I judge it not unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to offer to the Publick theſe few Lines, as well to prevent the miſchiefs of diſcontent and ſeditious fears, as to encourage all perſons to thoſe duties, and that Loyal behaviour, which our Heavenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and our Worldly Intereſt, require from us; and the rather I have been perſwaded to this attempt, becauſe there are ſuch numbers every where of men, of divers Principles and Deſigns, buſily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in undermining the Nations Tranquility, by labouring to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Peoples Affections from their Superiours, by aſperſing his wiſeſt Proceedings and Actions, and by ſpreading abroad the dangerous Seeds of Diſtruſt, Suſpicions, and Rebellion; chiefly in this juncture of time, ſince the Diſcovery of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot; now that Mens minds are apt to take ill impreſſions, the Malice of ſome is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable in divulging the greateſt Improbabilities, which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs have ill Effects and Conſequences attending them. It is not long ſince we have ſmarted under the woeful Sequels of ſuch Unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Practices, which ſhould oblige all men of reaſon to be cautious how they entertain and give encouragement to any thing that may leſſen the Reverence to Government, or divert us from our Duty; for let the Idolaters of Liberty ſay what they will, a Kingdom can never flouriſh whiles Authority is diſ-reſpected; and a Government is never ſafe when People give themſelves the liberty to caſt all manner of abuſes upon the lawful Governours. The contempt of Laws is the next door to Rebellion; and the Slanders faſtened unjuſtly upon thoſe that execute them, are near a-kin to Murder and Aſſaſſination. If the tongue wounds the Name, the Hand will ſcarce ſpare the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if opportunity were offered; and the rather we ſhould take heed how we entertain, or are inſtrumental in ſpreading abroad ill Reports
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53321:3"/>of the Sacred Perſons of our Governours, or of their Government, becauſe we ſee confirmed to us, that this is the Method which their Enemies and ours obſerve to bring us to our ruine. That we may therefore better ſecure our ſelves from ſuch dreadful Calamities here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and now from the wicked impreſſions of diſaffected Perſons, that we may quiet the Clamours and Fears of jealous Souls, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage men to a right eſteem and reſpect of our truly Religious King, and to the duties that tend to his preſervation and ours, from the Fury and Malice of our irreconcileable Enemies: I ſhall firſt give my Reader a ſhort Narrative of ſeveral Inſtances obſervable in our Princes Reign, of his love to his People, of his gracious Diſpoſition, and of his ſincerity and care in the preſervation of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: 2. I ſhall examine what Duties our own intereſt, and the preſent condition of the Nation, in relation to our Enemies abroad and at home require from us.</p>
            <p>Never any Prince hath ſuffered more from Rebellious Subjects than ours; never any more diſobliged, and more cruelly handled. By the late Civil Wars he was driven out of all his Inheritance, forced to ſeek for ſhelter in Forreign Nations, after that he had ſeen his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther barbarouſly murthered, his Nobles and faithful Servants maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, his Friends and Relations perſecuted, and their Eſtates ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and yet never any more merciful to his greateſt Enemies. When God was pleaſed to reſtore his Sacred Majeſty to his Throne and Kingdoms, and with him Religion and Peace, how gracious hath he ſhewn himſelf to his fierceſt Perſecutors. He hath not diminiſh'd any thing of their Eſtates, who endeavour'd to take all from him. He hath not attempted upon their Lives, who labour'd to deprive him of his: Nay in all his Majeſties Actings, in relation to publick or private concerns, ſince his happy Reſtauration, we may all take notice of his rare and Chriſtian diſpoſition, and of his conſtant endeavours to oblige the Nation. At his firſt appearance upon the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> of his own accord he granted a General Act of Oblivion, to ſilence all our fears, to ſtop the mouth of our Jealouſies, to prevent the active mallice of ſome men, to ſecure our lives and fortunes, to heal up all National Wounds which had been bleeding too long, and ſettle that Peace and Tranquillity which we have enjoyed at home ever ſince. His juſt reſentment might have taken notice of thoſe who had enriched themſelves with the Plunder of his people, and the Spoils of his Imperial Crown: The laws of Retalliation would have juſtified the Sequeſtration of the Sequeſtrator's ill-gotten Goods; but his majeſty's Wiſdom and Goodneſs ſmothered all his Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53321:3"/>in a gracious Pardon, and gave, to the peace and quietneſs of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> People, thoſe Eſtates and Riches which he might have juſtly and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taken to himſelf by a due Execution of Juſtice. He was content to loſe the great advantages which Divine Providence put into his hands, out of a ſpecial regard to the good of the Nation, and, in Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Royal Father, (that couragious Martyr) act in this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion more like a good Chriſtian, than like a powerful King.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the Princes mentioned in holy or prophane Literature, I find none ſo gracious, ſo merciful, and ſo ready to forgive offences, as ours hath been: I find none more provok'd by the Cruelty and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of his Subjects, and none ſo willing to ſpare the lives of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour, in whoſe peaceable Reign the Prince of Peace, the Lord Jeſus was born, was dignified by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate with this Honourable Title, <hi>The Father of the People,</hi> becauſe he was of an admirable diſpoſition: But we all know how cruel his <hi>Triumvirate</hi> was, and the beginning of his Empire was ſtained with the blood of the Nobleſt Families of <hi>Rome. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpius Trajanus</hi> was an excellent Prince, not guilty of the extravagancies of his Predeceſſors, and yet he could not pardon the offences of his Subjects without a bloody Compenſation. His Succeſſor <hi>Adrianus</hi> was ſo merciful, that he offered his Diadem to a Noble Traytor, who had harbour'd the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble thought of murdering his Prince; yet in ſeveral occaſions he gave liberty to his Paſſion and Revenge to ſpill the blood of the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Likewiſe amongſt the people of God, who more Religious and devout than <hi>David,</hi> a Man after Gods own Heart; yet his Vengeance would not ſuffer the gray hairs of <hi>Joah</hi> and <hi>Shimei</hi> to go down in peace to their Graves, though the latter had acted againſt him but with his Tongue; whereas many of this Nation, whoſe Hands and Tongues, if not their Hearts, have been acting againſt our merciful Prince, have been pardoned, ſuffered to enjoy their Eſtates in peace, protected by his Laws, and many of ability preferr'd and imployed. Though theſe kindneſſes have been done to private Perſons and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and they have chiefly reap'd the benefit of his Majeſties graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſpoſition, the whole Kingdom is thereby obliged to his Majeſty, becauſe in the forgiveneſs of ſuch Offenders, he hath had an Eye to the Publick good, peace and ſatisfaction of all his Subjects, rather than to his juſt Reſentment. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Meek Man, yet how many hundreds and thouſands were made Examples of his Juſtice, and Gods Wrath, for their Rebellions; few or none pardoned. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, the firſt Chriſtian Emperour's Name is ſacred in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of men; he forgave his Enemies, advanced Religion, incouraged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53321:4"/>Piety, yet he imbrued his Fatherly hands in the blood of his own Son and Heir <hi>Criſpus,</hi> upon the ſuſpition of a Rebellion. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour was a brave and an excellent Prince, yet the Inhabitants of <hi>Antioch</hi> complain of the promiſcuous killing of their Citizens in the Emperours rage. <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> the Law-giver of the World, could not give Laws to his own paſſions, nor ſave <hi>Belliſanius</hi> and <hi>Narſes,</hi> his two great Generals, from the cruel hands of his Empreſs <hi>Theodora.</hi> I might run over all the Hiſtories of former times, from the beginning of the World to this day, and mention to you the nobleſt, the rareſt, and moſt merciful Princes in forreign Nations, and in this, yet I dare affirm, and do offer my ſelf to prove from a certain knowledge of the Hiſtories of the World, that I may ſay I have perus'd, that there was never any King, or Soveraign Prince, neither in <hi>England,</hi> nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, who hath been ſo gracious, ſo compaſſionate and merciful to his People, as our King <hi>Charles;</hi> neither hath any Reign been more free from ſhedding of blood; never any Government more mild and happy; never any Prince leſs ruled by violence and intereſt, nor more govern'd than himſelf, by that Sacred Maxim of his Royal Father; <hi>The ſetled Laws of theſe Kingdoms are the moſt excellent Rules a King can govern by.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where are the Widows and Orphans amongſt us that can complain of the unjuſt murder of their Relations? Where is the Family ruined by the Confiſcation of its Eſtate and Patrimony? Where can we meet with any particular inſtance of his Majeſties over-ruling the ordinary courſe of Law and Juſtice. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. and our former Kings, would ſometimes give place to wrath, anger, and revenge; and their Wills ſometimes took the place of Laws: But where can we meet with any ſuch Example in our days? Where is there a perſon either Condemned, or Executed, or deprived of an Eſtate, by our Princes Command alone? Many have received their Lives and Eſtates from him, which had been forfeited by Law; but to this very day, none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver loſt either Lives or Fortunes to gratifie his Majeſties will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; even in this late wicked Plot againſt his Royal Perſon, he hath not puniſh'd any man but by courſe of Law.</p>
            <p>Is not this a happineſs for all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, for Poor and Rich, to live under ſuch a reaſonable Government, and gracious a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and where Law and Equity, Juſtice and Conſcience ſway the Scepter, where Power and the Regal Authority are never uſed, but in vindication, and for the execution of righteous Laws; though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> never intended to obſerve any meaſures of Reaſon, Conſcience or Humanity with his Majeſties Perſon and People, but in a ſecret and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53321:4"/>private way intended to fill the Land with Aſſaſſinations and Murders; nevertheleſs, he obſerves a Legal Method, and proceeds againſt them by ſuch means as are juſtifiable before God and Man: His Majeſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers them over to a Court of Judicature, to have a fair Tryal for their Lives; he ſuffers them to anſwer for themſelves, and leaves them to an impartial <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Jury.</hi> In forreign Nations ſuch Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Publick Safety would have been pull'd in pieces, as the <hi>De Witts;</hi> cut down and mangled by the rude Rabble, as <hi>Sejanus</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Aſſaſſins of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and of <hi>Henry</hi> the III. of <hi>France,</hi> and many others: They would not have had the patience to ſee them alive, who had reſolved upon ſo cruel a deſign, as to murder the King and his People without cauſe: But the World ſees the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Natures, the Excellency of the Principles of our Religion, and the Juſtice of our King, who is willing to make his moſt deſperate Enemies ſenſible of it in their own perſons, without any paſſion, which hath never carried him to act againſt them, but in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular way. And though ſome of them had forfeited their Eſtates by Law, and it had been but a piece of Juſtice to reduce their Poſterity to poverty, who intended to make ſo many poor Families in this Land; yet to the Eternal praiſe of his Majeſty be it ſpoken, he hath not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to take ought of their Eſtates, but hath reſtored ſince his Reſtauration, to the Children of many Rebels, Traytors, and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, the Patrimonies belonging to their Fore-fathers, it is therefore a moſt unreaſonable Aſperſion, and a wicked Slander, proceeding from the Shop of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and his bloody Jeſuits, to report any thing amiſs of his Majeſties moſt Excellent Government: As Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> hath very well taken notice, it hath been the deſign of thoſe Troublers of Peace, to make us ſtand in fear of an Arbitrary Government; and to faſten upon his Majeſty, and his proceedings, the moſt abuſive Lyes: but let any man run over the paſſages of his good Reign, he ſhall have no cauſe to ſuſpect what there is not the leaſt colour to believe.</p>
            <p>The ſuſpitions and jealouſies in relation to Religion, are as plainly ſcandalous and unlikely; it is ſufficiently known, how zealous his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath always been in the profeſſion of the true Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his Infancy: It was the Advice of his Royal Father, <hi>Above all, I would have you, as I hope you are already, well grounded and ſetled in your Religion; the beſt Profeſſion of which I have ever eſteem'd that of the Church of</hi> England: <hi>In this I charge you to perſevere, as coming neareſt to Gods Word for Doctrine, and to the Primitive Examples for Government.</hi> According to this direction our King hath behaved himſelf ſo, that neither fear, favour, nor intereſt, could ever draw him from this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53321:5"/>In his Baniſhment his Majeſty alone knows the greatneſs of his Tryals, and we and all the World the conſtancy of his mind.</p>
            <p>Here the whole World might have ſeen the Religion of King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. Neither the love nor glory of a Crown, nor the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the World, nor the advantages of Life could prevail upon him to waver in the leaſt from that excellent Religion and Faith, for which the King his Father ſpilt his blood, and which Chriſt and his Apoſtles have recommended to us; or to accept of the Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions: And ſince his Majeſties return to his Honour and Dignity, which may be look'd upon as a Reward of his Fidelity, as a glorious and honourable acknowledgment of Divine Providence of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce's faithfulneſs to the Profeſſion of the true Proteſtant Religion, and a Teſtimonial from God himſelf of his reality in his Faith, ſufficiently evidenced to all the World by the wonderful Circumſtances of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſtauration. I ſay, ſince his Majeſties return, how many plain and undoubted Teſtimonies hath he given us of his ſincerity in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Profeſſion and Reſolution, to maintain it in his Kingdoms againſt all Diſſenters and Oppoſers. His Royal Father left him this Charge: <hi>I do require and intreat you, as your Father and you King, that you never ſuffer your Heart to receive the leaſt check againſt, or diſaffection from the true Religion eſtabliſh'd in the Church of</hi> England: <hi>I tell you, I have tried it, and after much ſearch, and many diſputes, have concluded it to be the beſt in the World; not only in the Community as Chriſtian, but alſo in the ſpecial Notion, as reformed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore as ſoon as he was ſettled by the advice of his Loyal Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, he reſtored the Orders and Government of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which in the approved judgment of the King his Father is the beſt in the World, becauſe it is the moſt conformable in Doctrine and Practice, to Chriſt, his holy Apoſtles, and and the Primitive Church, as he expreſly declares: And to ſecure this moſt excellent Religion the better, by removing all the cauſes of diſſention, and Obſtacles that ſeem'd to hinder ſuch as had received contrary principles from em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing it, the Kings Majeſty yielded to an amendment of certain things which gave offence. What could have been deſired more from generous and a gracious Prince, than was then granted in complyance with the peoples weakneſs and miſtakes? The Nation was then, through the diſorders that had been in Church and State, ſplit into many pieces, and ſad diviſions: Mens judgments were poſſeſſed with unreconcileable Prejudices and ſtrange Principles, in oppoſition to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which they would not, nor could not ſpeedily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. It was therefore judged convenient to grant them time, and yet to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53321:5"/>eſtabliſh thoſe Law as might both declare to the World His Majeſties conſtancy in the true Proteſtant Religion, and direct them that were Diſſenters to embrace it. Examine but the Royal proclamations, and the Acts of Parliament, and ſee what they ſay, and it will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the Kings Majeſty never had any deſign, ſince his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor before, but to ſettle, protect, favour, and maintain, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Royal Promiſe, the true Proteſtant Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it was eſtabliſh'd in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s, King <hi>James</hi>'s, and his Martyred Father's days.</p>
            <p>And if not withſtanding, out of his royal goodneſs and wiſdom, the Laws againſt Papiſts were not always ſtrictly put in Execution, it was becauſe the neceſſities of the Kingdom, and the good of the Publick did ſo require it, for the preſervation of Peace, and the better ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Truth. Fire and Sword are not always ſeaſonable againſt Diſſenters in Religion: It belongs to a King to mitigate his Laws, and ſuit them to Times and Caſes: He is not always bound to obſerve them in all their rigour and exactneſs, neither doth ſuch proceedings conſiſt with the general good and happineſs of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; though the ſurious zeal of inconſiderate Subjects may ſometimes wiſh for the contrary. But, as in diſtempered Bodies the Phyſician doth not always obſerve the ſame Rules of his Art, nor apply the ſame Remedies; but changeth and altereth them according to the Diet, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Pulſe, Country, Air, and other Circumſtances of the Patient: So it becomes a wife Prince to handle the Diſtempers of Church and State, in ſuch a manner as may anſwer the univerſal good, the chief end of Government, and prevent the increaſe of the Diſeaſe. It is therefore a grand preſumption, for every petty Fellow, and ignorant Mechanick, to exclaim againſt his Superiours Actions in ſuch a caſe, when he is not capable to underſtand the great Reaſons of Sate that govern them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Papiſts did ſcemingly expreſs their Duty and Allegiance to the King, out of a deſign as it is now ſuppoſed by ſome, when he was in his Baniſhment, when many Proteſtants were unable to do him ſervice, but with their Prayers and Wiſhes. After his happy return, could he do any thing leſs than grant them ſome freedom under his good Government, for which many of them had taken up Arms againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? It was but juſt, whiles they confined their Religion within their own Breaſts, and profeſſed to live as peaceable Subjects, and quiet in their Offices and Eſtates, that they ſhould reap ſome of the Fruits, and taſte of the ſweetneſs of that Reign, for which many of them had ventur'd their Lives and Fortunes. As they had a ſhare in the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53321:6"/>it was but juſt that they ſhould have alſo a ſhare in the happineſs that ſucceeded: As they have been concerned in his Majeſties Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Reaſon and Conſcience obliged him at firſt to ſuffer them to have an Intereſt in his Reſtauration and happineſs. This is ſufficient to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie our Kings gracious Proceedings towards the Papiſts from all jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and ſuſpicion, and to make it appear that his Grants and Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances proceeded not from any approbation of the Popiſh Idolatries and Superſtitions, but from a Principle of Juſtice; not from an allowance of their Religion and Abominations, but of their Perſons, and faithfulneſs to him in his diſtreſs, which had obliged him in requital to ſhew them ſome favour.</p>
            <p>And not only to them his Majeſty hath given ſeveral Expreſſions of Royal goodneſs, but alſo to all Diſſenters from the Religion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Though the Laws are ſevere againſt Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and Conventiclers, whiles they are peaceable and not mutinous, though their Practices are of ill conſequence, and not agreeable with Law, yet ſo great is his condeſcention as to ſuffer them in their way, without diſturbing their Meetings, according to this Chriſtian Speech which hath been often heard from his Majeſty. <hi>I will never trouble any for his Conſcience, but let no Man trouble, nor diſturb my Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Papiſts had not plotted the Nations ruine, and agreed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to murder both Prince and People, they might have yet continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely in the enjoyment of their Religion, and of as much privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as they could reaſonably deſire under the Government of ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable a Monarch. No perſon would have dream'd to diſturb them in their Privacies and ſecret Devotions: They might have lived and died, without any fear of the Execution of the Laws, in the fruition of their Eſtates and Places, with as much liberty as the Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. We all began to look upon them with kindneſs, to eſteem them as our Brethren and good Countrymen, and to favour them in many reſpects: But how ſtrangely have we been miſtaken and deceived, let the World judge. However this is our comfort, that their malice and bloody deſigns intended againſt us were cauſeleſs, and without any provocation on our parts. Neither his ſacred Majeſty, nor any of his people did ever before give them any diſtaſte, but in harmleſs Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes; in which they had as much freedom to anſwer as any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Divine.</p>
            <p>But when this helliſh Plot broke out, to our great amazement, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be judged unreaſonable if they are reſtrained by Authority, and the ancient Laws revived againſt theſe new Traytors, that offer for Religion to riſe in Arms againſt their King and Country. It cannot
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53321:6"/>be thought unreaſonable if their Leaders, and the Chieftains of their Rebellion be ſecured, that they may not put in practice thoſe Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man purpoſes unto which they had encouraged their ſilly Proſelites. It cannot be thought unjuſt, if Governours and People require from them ſecurity for their good behaviour for the time to come, and ſuch Oaths as may oblige them to a peaceable Behaviour, if any ſuch there be that hath that good influence upon their wide Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and licentious Principles.</p>
            <p>His Majeſties care to prevent the miſchiefs which they intended againſt us, our Religion, and Nation, hath been anſwerable to and no leſs than his favour and goodneſs to them before. Truth, this Conſpiracy is ſo hainous, that at the firſt Relation it may not ſeem ſtrange, if a good Prince, who is as much perſwaded of his peoples Affection for him, as he knows his love and mindfulneſs of their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and ſafety, could not eaſily believe it; it being ſo unlikely an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, that Poſterity may look upon this Plot, as ſome in our days do upon the <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon,</hi> as upon a Romantick Story, or a Politick Invention, or a State Trick, and give no more credit to it than to the Hiſtories of Grand <hi>Cirus,</hi> or of <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwick,</hi> or of <hi>Amadis de Gaule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a matter of ſo great a moment, it did become a Prince of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Judgment, and Wiſdom, to weigh the Teſtimonies, examin the Circumſtances, and conſider all particulars, before he ought to paſs a determinate Sentence in this Caſe. But now the Evidences are as plain as the Sun, now that it appears that this Barbarity was really har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in the breaſts of ſome of the <hi>Popiſh Party;</hi> now that we ſee their Malice and Cruelty written with the indelible Characters of the innocent Blood of an eminent Magiſtrate and Martyr, whoſe only Crime was that he knew theirs, and their horrid Proceedings; now that we ſee, by his unexpected Murder, what our King and People were to receive from the mercileſs hands of theſe men, who can deny it? Certainly God hath infatuated their Wicked Counſels for the good of our People, Nation, and Religion, and ſuffered their furious Zeal to begin one Tragedy which they intended ſhould have acted many more. But by this Cruel Murder they have given us a clearer Proſpect of their Diabolical Deſigns, and allarm'd us all in defence of our Perſons, King, and Country, againſt ſuch future Inhumani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: They have hereby liſted up the Mask, and ſhewn to all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the fearful Features of their diſguiſed Religion, and declared to us all what Mallice and Cruelty governs them, what Wickedneſs they would commit, if Power and Authority were in their hands. O Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53321:7"/>Impiety! could you offer to ſtrike at a Breaſt full of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and affection for your perſons? Could you attempt upon a life upon which depends all our lives and fortunes? Your Inhumanity is the more inexcuſable, and not to be parallell'd amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> and worſt of Infidels, whoſe Principles ſuffer them not to be wicked to their Benefactors.</p>
            <p>This Circumſpection of our merciful Prince deſerves our Eternal Praiſes, rather than the Abuſes of diſaffected people. Why ſhould the <hi>Papists</hi> plot againſt his life, for being our Friend? This is an Injuſtice guilty of the moſt grievous folly and palpable miſtakes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from Ignorance, and the not obſerving the great care that his Majeſty hath taken to diſcover and prevent all the miſchiefs intended againſt us and his Government; for, upon the firſt Diſcovery of the Plot his Majeſty gave ſpeedy Orders to his privy Council to proceed in the Examination of this great buſineſs: According to his Royal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands they ſate regularly twice every Week to ſift out the matter, and when they found the truth of it by undoubted Circumſtances, they ſent to apprehend divers of the Conſpirators; examin'd them ſeverally to ſift out the matter; afterwards they committed others to Cuſtody; uſing in this and all other Proceedings all the Care and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie immaginable. All perſons chiefly concerned or ſuſpected were ſought for; and as many as were found were ſent to Priſon, to be tryed according to the Order of Law. It is true, our people laid not violent hands upon them: We did not tear them in pieces as they went about, nor diſ-member them upon bare ſuſpicions of Treaſon: We did not mangle their Bodies, nor exerciſe our rage upon theſe bloody men.</p>
            <p>The Proceedings of our King and Council were agreeable with the Rules of Humanity, Reaſon, and Equity. The Malefactors were ſecured, and delivered over into the hands of Juſtice, to be treated according to the Laws of the Land. They had fair Tryals for their lives; men of Conſcience and Worth judged them Guilty by moſt undeniable Teſtimonies: They had liberty to anſwer for themſelves, and to defend their own Cauſe: They were heard with patience and Chriſtian moderation; and there was nothing acted againſt them, but was ſuitable to Chriſts precepts and his Holy Goſpel. If all the Proceedings be obſerved, we ſhall find nothing more reaſonable, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more Chriſtian and juſt, than the Actions of our King and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours in this Caſe. They are ſufficiently juſtified from all ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of Cruelty on one hand, and from all neglect or carleſneſs on the other. Can the <hi>Papiſts</hi> now find fault, if they are abridged in ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53321:7"/>reſpects from that liberty which they intended to abuſe in ſo wicked a Plot? Can they blame our Governours, for ſeeking ſo carefully to preſerve themſelves, the King's Majeſty, his Dignity, Government, and Religion, from their Inhumanities? And on the other ſide, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, let us obſerve the care and diligence of his Majeſty, and of our Governours, to ſecure the nations peace from <hi>Popery</hi> and the Conſpirators.</p>
            <p>After the Plot was fully diſcovered, his Majeſty re-inforced his Guards, and gave liberty to the Trained-Bands to ſtand up in their own defence; Care was alſo taken to ſecure and ſeize upon all ſuſpected perſons. About this time the <hi>Papiſts</hi> thought to have ſmothered the noiſe of the Plot, in the Death and Blood of a diligent Inquirer into their proceedings, Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> whom they inhumanely murdered. When he was miſſing divers Reports were raiſed, and Slanders faſtened upon him: They that were guilty of this black Crime endeavoured to make us believe the greateſt Improbabilities; <hi>That he hadkill'd himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. But the manner of his lying, with all the Circumſtances, convinc'd the Coroner and Jury, aſſiſted by Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions on purpoſe, that he had been baſely and inhumanely murder'd. The boldneſs and deſperateneſs of this Villany awaken'd the whole Nation, and cauſed his Majeſty immediately to ſend forth his Royal Proclamation, for the ſeeking out and finding the Actors in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane murder, commanding them to give intelligence of all ſuch Diſcoveries to one of the principal Secretaries of State: For their greater encouragement, five hundred pounds were promiſed to them, with a Pardon, if the Diſcoverer were any ways guilty. I cannot here expreſs what diſpleaſure his Majeſty received, how ſenſible he was at the loſs of ſo uſeful a Subject, who dyed for his care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the Service of his Prince and Country. The Vertues and Excellency of his perſon, the Integrity of his Behaviour, his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Piety, Prudence, and Diſcretion in his Place and Calling, caus'd his Majeſty, and all that knew him to mourn for him. But the baſeneſs of his Murder, the Treachery of his Aſſaſſins, the Marks of their Cruelty leſt upon his dead Body, call'd for Vengeance from man as well as from God; which every good Subject was ſo much the more concerned to ſee executed upon the bloody Butchers, in regard of their impudency, and the boldneſs of the Attempt, wilfully to betray and murder an innocent perſon, a famous Juſtice of Peace, in a Royal Pallace; a Juſtice known to his Majeſty by his great Services, and to all the City by his good behaviour and Religious life: To mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him within the protection of the Guards; and having carryed his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53321:8"/>Body into the Fields, and caſt it away as a Dog, to endeavour next to murder his Name and Reputation with vile Slanders. All theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances could not but ſtir up the Juſtice of a good King, by the puniſhment of the Inhumane Villains, to ſecure other men from ſuch like Inhumanities, and declare to all the World his ſorrow, grief and diſpleaſure for ſuch a barbarous Act. For the better finding out of the Murderers, his Majeſty cauſed a diligent enquiry and ſearch to be made, ſummon'd and commanded all his Officers and good Subjects to do the like: And when he was inform'd that ſome were willing to come in and reveal the Murder, but the fear of the Conſequences, as of the revengeful hand of the Friends, or of the other Murderers, made them cautious how they indanger'd themſelves: His Majeſty, for their incouragement, by a ſecond Proclamation, promis'd on the Word of a King, <hi>That if any perſon ſhould ſpeedily make diſcovery, he ſhould not only receive the Reward of</hi> 500 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>and Pardon promiſed, but his Majeſty would take ſuch effectual care for the ſecurity of ſuch Diſcoverer, as he ſhould in reaſon propoſe.</hi> What other ways and methods could be propoſed more likely to bring this Murder to light, and the wicked Varlets to their deſerved puniſhment? They have by Gods goodneſs proved ſo effectual, that this <hi>Popiſh</hi> act of Inhumanity, with all its Circumſtances, is generally known, and fully underſtood. The guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons were ſecur'd; ſearch, and a diligent enquiry was made for them that were fled; <hi>Green, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> were tryed, found guilty, condemned to be hang'd: Which Sentence was accordingly executed upon them; two ſuffer'd upon the 21. of <hi>Febr. Berry</hi> was Reprieved for a few days, but is now executed alſo.</p>
            <p>During his Majeſties moſt peaceable Reign, as he hath always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed an abhorrency of the ſhedding of Innocent Blood, ſo he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been diligent and careful to ſee to the due execution of the Laws upon bloody-minded men, and to cauſe his Juſtice to take away the Lives of thoſe who cannot ſuffer his good Subjects to live in peace. As in this occaſion his Juſtice hath been remarkable to the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Piety towards God, and care for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, in other reſpects, have been no leſs viſible; for conſidering the number, the power and devilliſh ſubtilties of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and that therefore without Gods goodneſs, protection, and watchfulneſs over us, we are in continual danger to be oppreſs'd by our vigilant and malicious Adverſaries, his Majeſty by a Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on called upon all his good Proteſtant Subjects, to humble themſelves before God, to aſcribe to him the glory of all our Deliverances, to amend ſincerely our lives, and put our ſelves into ſuch a diſpoſition, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53321:8"/>may reaſonably expect Gods protection for the time to come: A me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod always obſerv'd by good Kings and Princes, when their Enemies were numerous and great. Queen <hi>Heſter</hi> ſent to <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> to humble themſelves before God when <hi>Haman</hi>'s Conſpiracy was diſcover'd and known. The King of <hi>Nineveh</hi> commanded a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and a ſtrict Faſt within his Dominions, when <hi>Jonah</hi> foretold the Judgment of God by Fire that was to conſume that ſinful City: And <hi>David, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and all the good Kings of <hi>Judea,</hi> took the ſame courſe to divert Gods approaching Judgments: And as their Prayers and Humiliation proved effectual, ſo as to prevail upon the goodneſs of God, and oblige to withdraw the Sword of his Juſtice ſtretch'd out over their heads: So likewiſe I hope God will forgive the great ſins of this Nation, preſerve his Majeſty in proſperity and health, many any many years, and keep his Royal Perſon, and us all, from the bloody hands of all <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Codfrey</hi> this Plot appear'd ſo plain, and with ſo many hainous and dreadful Circumſtances, that every one was fully convinc'd of the reality of this Helliſh Deſign; which, if not prevented in time, would have drown'd us all in Rivers of our own blood. To hinder therefore all ſequels of the Plot, and take from the <hi>Papiſts</hi> the power and opportunity of putting any part of it in execution, his Majeſty on the 30th of <hi>Octob.</hi> iſſues out his Royal Proclamation, to command all <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> to depart from <hi>Weſtmin-Hall, Somerſet-Houſe, S. James</hi>'s, the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and not to come within ten miles of theſe places. By this means his Majeſty hath provided for the ſecurity of his Royal Perſon; he hath hinder'd our Enemies from meeting together in numbers; he hath broke the Neck of all <hi>Popiſh</hi> Reſolutions, Conſultations, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and Rebellion in the City, or near his Royal abode. And leſt they ſhould gather together in any conſiderable numbers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and raiſe there any ſtirs, to the diſquietneſs of his Majeſties Subjects and Government, by another Proclamation of the 10th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> his Majeſty firſt declares his knowledge and perſwaſion of the dangerous and wicked Plots and Deſigns of <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> againſt his Perſon and Government, tending to the ſubverſion of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law within this Realm: And then he ſtrictly commands all his Subjects, being above the age of 16 years, if they be, or ſhall be lawfully Convicted, to repair to their ſeveral abodes, and not to paſs above five miles from thence, upon pain that the Offenders ſhall loſe all their Eſtates moveable and immoveable. And becauſe ſome <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> have eſcap'd Conviction, through
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53321:9"/>the Indulgence and favour of his Majeſties Officers, he is pleas'd to command all ſuch as ſhall be reputed <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> though not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, if they obey not his Royal Orders, that they ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by tendring to them the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy; and in caſe of a refuſal, that they ſhall be treated according to the ſeverity of the Laws in ſuch caſes provided. And further, if they refuſe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to this his Majeſties Royal Commands, the Juſtices are order'd to ſignifie their Contempt to my Lord Chancellour, who is appointed to take that ſevere courſe which is agreeable with the Laws, and the Publick Safety: Only his Majeſty out of his Royal goodneſs is pleas'd to except ſuch as are hinder'd by ſickneſs, weakneſs of body, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and ſuch as are baniſh'd ten miles from the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Proclamation his Majeſty provides for the ſafety of his Subjects all over the Kingdom, and prevents the mallice of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> from breaking out in the Country at a diſtance, as it intended to break out in the Bowels of the City: Therefore they are hereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd within certain limits, and ſuch circumſpection is uſed, that thoſe who are willing to diſturb the Nation, ſhall not have the leaſt power to effect their deſires and deſigns.</p>
            <p>Though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of Note and Credit are generally accuſed for being acceſſary to, and acquainted with this Conſpiracy, his Majeſties Wiſdom, Chriſtian moderation and Juſtice, have endeavoured to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure none, but thoſe who are apparently guilty, and againſt whom there are evident proofs. On the reſt he lays ſuch Injunctious and Commands, as may keep them in peace; but thoſe he hath laboured to find out, and bring to their deſerved puniſhments.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ſome of them were fled, his Majeſty by his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the 20th of <hi>Novemb</hi> charges them to come in to their Tryals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the 10th of <hi>Decemb.</hi> and juſtifie themſelves from the Crime laid to their Charge, of deſigning to deſtroy the Kings Royal Perſon, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Government, and root out the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by Law; His Majeſty declares, if they will not ſurrender themſelves, that they ſhall be declar'd guilty of High-Treaſon by Law, commanding all his Officers and Loyal Subjects to endeavour to find out, and apprehend them; and for their incouragement, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty promiſeth them 100 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> as a Reward. And for the better diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of theſe Offenders, all Officers are commanded within their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and Precincts, to take the Names of all <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> above to years of age, and to deliver a Liſt of them to the Juſtices of the Peace, who are thereby ordered to ſend for them, and tender to them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53321:9"/>the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy; and in caſe of a refuſal, to bind them over to appear at the next Seſſions of the Peace, where they are to be treated according to law.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Proclamation his Majeſty gives an Expreſs Command to all his Officers in the Country, to proceed without delay to diſarm all ſuch perſons as ſhall refuſe to take the oaths; and promiſeth alſo ten pounds to every one who ſhall find any conſiderable quantity of Arms in the houſes of any <hi>Popiſh Recuſant,</hi> to be paid to them by the Sheriff of that County. Order is there likewiſe given to all Officers upon the Sea-coaſts, to uſe diligence in the taking of <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> and of other <hi>Engliſh Papiſts</hi> coming in or going out of the Realm, and to carry them before a Juſtice of the peace to take the Oaths; which if they refuſe, they are to be ſent to Goal, and their names to be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to his Majeſties Privy Council, that ſuch further courſe may be taken for the ſafety of his Majeſty, and of his Government, as to his Majeſties Royal Wiſdom ſhall be thought fit.</p>
            <p>The ſame day his majeſty, having taken notice of the numbers and wicked actings of <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> diſguiſed within the Realm, with an intent not only to draw his Subjects from the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh Idolatries,</hi> but alſo to ſet on foot divers trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Plots and Deſigns againſt his Majeſties Government, and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> was pleaſed by another Proclamation to charge all Magiſtrates, and other Officers, to uſe their utmoſt endeavour to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, apprehend, and commit to ſafe Cuſtody, in order to their Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, all <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and for the incouragement of every ſuch Diſcoverer, his Majeſty promiſeth twenty pounds for every <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Jeſuit</hi> apprehended, to be paid at the time of the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> have always been the Popes Emiſſaries in <hi>England,</hi> and have had a hand in all the Wars and Diſturbances in the Land, ſince the Reformation: They have been the Spies upon our Publick Peace, Tranquility, Government, Church and State; therefore our own preſervation calls upon us, to ſecure and treat them according to the Ancient Laws of the Realm, as our ſworn E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and the Diſturbers of the Nations Peace. By this laſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation therefore, every one may ſee how careful his Majeſty hath been to ſecure ſuch wicked perſons, and deliver them over to Juſtice, to hinder all their evil deſigns and purpoſes, and defend his Subjects Lives, Religion, and Eſtates, from this and all other damnable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in all Plots of this nature, when the chief Actors are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53321:10"/>either ſilent, or not apprehended, there remains ſomething ſecret which cannot eaſily come to light, for the better diſcovering of ſuch things, and the whole Deſign, with all its hainous and criminal cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, his Majeſty was pleas'd, on the 27th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proclamation, to declare and promiſe, <hi>That if any perſon would come in, and make any further diſcovery of the late horrid Deſign againſt his Majeſties Sacred Perſon Government, before the fifth day of</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, <hi>he ſhould have as a Reward a full Pardon, either for being guilty thereof, or for the concealment, and two hundred pounds in Money for ſuch a diſcovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are Rewards and Puniſhments, Promiſes and Threatnings, much vigilancy, circumſpection, and care imployed by his moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majeſty, to ſecure us and our Religion from the wicked deſigns of our <hi>Popiſh</hi> Enemies: Nothing that Wiſdom or Prudence can ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, hath been omitted for the Publick ſafety: And becauſe the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> Policy hath always invited over into their Schools, and Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſeveral Gentlemens Children, under a pretence of a better and a more ſpeedy Education, and a greater Proficiency in Learning, but purpoſely to infect them with their <hi>Popiſh Principles</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to the great prejudice of the Nation, as well as to the ruine of ſuch poor Souls, his Majeſty hath been pleaſed ſtrictly to forbid ſuch Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for the time to come, becauſe theſe Perſons, when they are grown up to years of underſtanding, and have learn'd their Leſſon perfectly, they are ſent back into <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Sapho</hi>'s Parrots and Birds were amongſt the Woods and Caves of <hi>Africa,</hi> upon the ſame Errand, to proclaim <hi>that the Pope he is God.</hi> Theſe Perſons are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to Religion and the Publick ſafety, for they are like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, they ſpread the Fire every where in this Field of <hi>England;</hi> they borrow from beyond the Seas that ſubtilty, which together with the courage and ſtrength of Reſolution, natural to our Nation, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them the moſt fiery and deſperate Enemies of our Religion and Government, and carries them to the boldeſt Attempts againſt the Lives of our Kings and Princes: Of this number were <hi>Pool, Campian, Garnet, Piercy, Catesby,</hi> and others of the ſame Principles.</p>
            <p>To prevent ſuch Evils for the time to come, and hinder our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentry from <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Infection, the Kings Majeſty ſent out his Proclamation on the 8th of <hi>January,</hi> to command home all ſuch young perſons as are in forreign Seminaries, and their Parents or Guardians to ſend for them ſpeedily, promiſing his gracious Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for their former offence, if they return according to his Majeſties Order; forbidding, for the future, any ſuch perſons to be ſent into
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53321:10"/>thoſe Forreign Schools of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and their Parents and Guardians to ſend them any relief: Beſides, his Majeſty declares in this Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; That he expects due obedience to this Command, and that ſuch as ſhall diſobey ſhall be puniſh'd according to Law, as well as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his high diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Here are ſeveral Proclamations in which all the ways and methods that can be imagined, to prevent the growth, the machinations and wicked deſigns of <hi>Popery,</hi> are carefully obſerved. All that may or can conduce to the ſettlement and ſecurity of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and the preſent Government is eſtabliſhed and commanded. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are baniſhed from Court, diſarmed in the Country, confin'd to their Dwellings, bound to their good behaviour; their Children are commanded away from <hi>Popiſh</hi> Schools, their <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are ſought for and impriſoned, penalties and rewards are promiſed and threatned for to encourage the Execution of the Laws. What greater Teſtimony of his Majeſties Sincerity to our Religion, and care of our Welfare, can we wiſh for? What means more effectual could be employed for that good purpoſe? What other Orders and Commands can we imagin ſeaſonable and ſit to ſecure our ſelves from <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Popery?</hi> But if theſe Commands and Proclamations have not met with an exact obedience in all reſpects and in all parts of the Land, I ſuppoſe it is the fault of ſome private Officers, who prefer their Obligations to, and intimacy with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to the performance of their Princes Orders, and a due obedience to his Commands. I am perſwaded no reaſonable people can juſtly deſire from a good King greater aſſurances of his reality in the <hi>Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> and of his reſolution to maintain it, than we have always had. In his Majeſties moſt gracious Speech, on the 9th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> to the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons when his Majeſty went to thank them for their care of his ſafety, and preſervation in theſe times of danger; he aſſures them, <hi>That he ſtudies as much their preſervation,</hi> and promiſeth <hi>to joyn with them in all the ways and means that may eſtabliſh a firm ſecurity of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion according to their hearts deſire.</hi> In his time his Majeſty tells them that they need not ſear, but for the time to come he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth <hi>to concur with them readily in all Bills and Acts which they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for the ſecurity of their Perſons and Religion, and deſires them to think of ſome more effectual means for the Conviction of Popiſh Recuſants.</hi> In the concluſion his Majeſty declares, <hi>That he is ready to do any thing that may give comfort and ſatisfaction to all his dutiful and Loyal Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words his Majeſty's Royal Sincerity and candour in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53321:11"/>appears as clear as the Sun in its ſplendour; and no reaſonable Perſon can deſire greater Evidences of his care of his peoples ſafety, of his reſolution to maintain the <hi>Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> and to keep <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> out of this Land, than his Majeſty hath lately given us.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe at the Prorogation of the laſt Parliament his Majeſty was pleaſed to tell them, <hi>That he would immediately enter upon disbanding the Army, and that he would let all the World ſee that there was nothing that he intended but for the good of the Kingdom, and for the ſafety of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That he would proſecute this Plot, and find out who were the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in it.</hi> And in the Concluſion his Majeſty promis'd, <hi>That he would take all the care that lay in his Power for the ſecurity of Religion, and the maintenance of it as it is now eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſame purpoſe his Majeſty declares in his gracious Speech to both houſes of Parliament lately aſſembled, <hi>That for the publick good, and ſatisfaction of all his Subjects, he had done many great things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, in order to our ſafety, his Majeſty in that Speech offers <hi>to confirm any new Law which they ſhall think ſeaſonable or neceſſary for the ſecuring of the Kingdom againſt Popery:</hi> and aſſures them, <hi>That with his life his Majeſty will defend the proteſtant Religion, and the Laws of this Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe Gracious Words and Promiſes this wife and Loyal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is encouraged to act in order for their own ſecurity as vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as they can. What now can any Prince ſay or do more in ſuch a caſe as this? He hath endeavoured to ſecure Religion from Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Plots, and Forreign Attempts: He hath ſet all Engines at work, and made it his whole and chief buſineſs to provide for our good, welfare, ſecurity, and the happineſs of the Kingdom, according to the pious and Religious Examples of the Royal Martyr, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Father, and of King <hi>James</hi> his Grand-father, under whoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments theſe Kingdoms and true Religion have long flouriſhed in Peace, and would never poſſibly have been ſo much diſturbed with Wars, Tumults, and Civil Diſſentions, had it not been for the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> that thruſt themſelves amongſt us. King <hi>James</hi> was ſenſible of their dangerous proceedings, therefore he enacted againſt them moſt wholeſome and juſt Laws, which cauſed them to attempt often upon his Sacred Life. For our late <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> we know by whom he was condemned to dye, before that Arch-Traytor and Uſurper <hi>Oliver</hi> and his Butchers brought him to his Tryal. The moſt noble Family of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> it ſeems, is not ſit for their unjuſt and ſuperſtitious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; they have been the nurſing Fathers of Gods true Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; they have defended Religion againſt their Idolatries with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53321:11"/>their Swords, Pens, and Blood; their noble and generous minds cannot ſtoop to acknowledge any other Superiour but God; they will not yield to their cruel purpoſes; therefore theſe wicked Traytors have alwayes laboured to cut off that moſt Religious Family: There can be no greater Teſtimony of our King being a true Proteſtant, than this, that the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Papiſts</hi> have declared him to be their Enemy, and have ſought to deſtroy him who is God's Anointed, and the beſt of princes.</p>
            <p>By theſe wicked Deſigns, and reſtleſs endeavours, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have from time to time drawn upon themſelves the hatred of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> People, anger'd the Governours of the Church and State, and obliged them to enact Laws againſt them, to reſtrain them from that Liberty which a great part of them never knew how to uſe with moderation and diſcretion in this Land.</p>
            <p>Their Proceedings and Attempts are not only diſconſonant with the peaceable temper and bleſſed Rules of Chriſts Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſo barbarous and inhuman, that we may juſtly wonder what ſpirit of madneſs poſſeſſeth their Souls; what cruel De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil prompts them to ſuch Actions, and makes them forget all ſenſe of Humanity: The ſettlement of their Religion, which is their ordinary pretence to excuſe their Tragedies, may blind the Conſciences of Fools; but Men of any reaſon may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Human not a Divine End of their Villanies: The <hi>Pope,</hi> and Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Agents the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are, care as little for the Salvation of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Souls, as it ſeems, they do for their Bodies. Were this Iſland a barren and a fruitleſs place, they would never take the pains to ſeek to ſubdue this Nation; but they are longing to finger again the <hi>Peter</hi>-pence, the Annates, the Firſt fruits, the Revenues, and diſpoſe of the ſat Benefices of this Land: This is their aim and end: To come to it they ſet all Engines a work, and dread not to ſpil Rivers of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood. But did but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, that are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſo forward and zealous to promote their <hi>Catholick Cauſe,</hi> know the weight and unſufferable burden of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Keys, did they but call to mind the Tyranny and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53321:12"/>of the former <hi>Popes</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and the Groans of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation when <hi>Popery</hi> had the Command, they would never be ſuch Fools to ſacrifice their lives to bring their Native Country to ſo great a Bondage, which our Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers could never bear: Is it not a madneſs for them that have a good King of their own, and a lawful Authority ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God over them, to ſtrive to murder him, and all his Generation, and ſet up a <hi>Pope,</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> a Stranger, who never intends to Reign amongſt us in Perſon, but to govern us by his Cardinals and proud Legats, and who will give to them the leaſt ſhare of their Country, when in his hands? Is it not a ſtrange madneſs, for Natives of <hi>England</hi> to ſeek to inthrall their Country to a Forreign Power, and the pleaſure of an Enemy? Have they no other way to exerciſe their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Courages, but by maſſacring their Brethren and Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks, for the Luſt and benefit of Imperious <hi>Italians,</hi> or <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</hi> Muſt Religion be the Cloak for this Villany and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? God, whoſe Power and Providence have preſerv'd this Church, and our Princes from barbarous deſigns of <hi>Roman</hi> Murderers, will I hope defend the Perſon and Life of our Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Gracious, Merciful, and Chriſtian King, from all <hi>Popiſh Conſpiracies.</hi> I pray God to awaken all Chriſtian Princes into a ſenſe of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Uſurpations, that they may ſhake off all the Fetters of this <hi>Italian</hi> Thraldom, the Bolts and Chains of the <hi>Popes</hi> Bondage.</p>
            <p>There is an old Prophecy amongſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which I have heard from ſome of their Doctors in the Schools, That an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> ſhall take the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> diſſolve the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and put a period to the <hi>Papacy.</hi> It is certain, from the 17th and 18th Chapters of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> that there is a time when God will bring that proud City to ruine, and treat her in the ſame manner as ſhe hath treated other Nations; who knows but God may raiſe up ſome brave Soul that may endeavour to free the World, and all Nations from ſo great a Plague, and ſet at liberty ſo many Chriſtian Princes, that ſcarce dare think of delivering themſelves, for fear of a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailack,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53321:12"/>a Stab, or a Cup of Poyſon? who knows but that Providence may pitch upon, and Commiſſion a Native of this Land to puniſh <hi>Rome</hi> for her Murders, Burnings, and Villanies committed by her Emiſſaries in our Cities, more than in any under the Sun. I am certain this agrees with the methods of Gods proceedings in the World, as well as with his holy Word; for in former Ages, the overthrow of Empires have been commonly brought to paſs, by thoſe Nations who have been moſt afflicted and diſtreſſed by them, in the times of their proſperity.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, as our good King hath been, and is yet vigilant and careful to protect us, our Religion, and Country, from ruine and deſtruction; and he neglects no labour, ſpares no coſt, declines no trouble nor pains for the general good of his People, for their ſafety, honour, and intereſt, I think we are obliged by all the reaſon of the World, to make him ſome Returns, to aſſiſt him in ſo pious a work, as the Eſtabliſhment of Religion, and the ſecurity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean our ſelves as thankful and dutiful Subjects. I ſhall not here mind you of the Commands of God, nor heap together paſſages of Scripture that tell us, that we muſt be ſubject to the Powers, becauſe there is no Power but of God; that they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation; that we muſt obey for Conſcience ſake; that we muſt love, honour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect him as Gods Vicegerent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall only mind my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what the preſent poſture of Affairs, in relation to our own good, and his Majeſties vigilancy and care in providing for our ſafety, require from us; and what preſent Obligations we lye under, to perform thoſe things which both our Intereſt and Duty demand from us.</p>
            <p>This Helliſh Conſpiracy of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that hath now at laſt awaken'd us into a ſenſe of our great danger, hath been many years contriving and deſigning; as the Deſign was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately and ſubtilly laid, it was to be carried on with vigour, and would handly have wanted the aſſiſtance of forreign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Armies: If the firſt Train had taken fire, this Church
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53321:13"/>and State had been infallibly blown up, and caſt into a Civil War: God hath been merciful to us in the diſcovery and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of it.</p>
            <p>But the Perſons chiefly concerned, and the vaſt Treaſures heap'd together for the carrying on of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Deſigns, are not like to ſit and remain idle after this diſappointment; our proceedings, and the Execution of the Inſtruments, will in all probability oblige them to take other meaſures to carry on their wicked purpoſes with more ſecreſie than before; our Diviſions and unreconcileableneſs give them no ſmall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and incouragement to make freſh Attempts, which God of his Mercy fruſtrate: However, our Nation is not yet out of danger by the death of a few Malefactors; we have Enemies both at home and abroad, that watch for, and endeavour our deſtruction: His Majeſty, you ſee, hath imployed his utmoſt endeavour for our ſafety, ſecurity, and happineſs, and is yet reſolved to imploy all his power to defend and protect us, and our Religion, from all Popiſh Deſigns. It concerns us not to be idle, but in our ſeveral places to contribute to our own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and preſervation, to give our aſſiſting hand to our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Prince, in ſo bleſſed a work as the ſettlement of our Religion and Government, chiefly in theſe particulars, which I ſhall recommend to the peruſal and practice of all ſincere <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Let every one of us in our ſeveral Places and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, watch with diligence over our Enemies deſigns and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at home and abroad; and in all occurrences that we may juſtly ſuſpect; let us carefully give Intelligence to Authority, take heed of concealing out of friendſhip or fear, reſolutions and actions that are ominous to Prince or people: They that are abroad in forreign Courts, have a great advantage to learn all Tranſactions, and underſtand the deſignments of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions; for ſuch weighty matters can never be ſo ſecretly intended, but they muſt be diſcovered to many, whoſe hands and aſſiſtances are needful to further and advance them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us all return to his Majeſty the Tribute of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53321:13"/>ſincere, and Loyal affections, out of a ſenſe of his care of our welfare. The Crown of it ſelf is heavy, our Enemies render it heavier by their daily Conſpiracies; let us not, who are true Subjects, add more weight and trouble to the Crown of our good King, by unreaſonable jealouſies, and unreaſonable fears and murmurings; but in our ſeveral Spheres, and according to our Abilities, let us alleviate as much as in us lies, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Burden: And by all dutiful expreſſions of our love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects diſcover to him our ſenſibleneſs of his continual care of our ſafety and welfare.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed we diſcredit not his Authority, vilifie his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or diſhonour his Government, by any wicked and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Reports, of our own, or others invention; for this kind of Ingratitude which his Majeſty never deſerv'd from the Hands of his Proteſtant Subjects, nor any others, will breed ill blood amongſt the People, and afflict the Heart of a good Prince.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us Proteſtants be ſo ſenſible of our danger and good, as to reunite again in the Profeſſion of one Religion, and in the publick worſhip of our God; that our Enemies ſeeing that their often repeated malice hath caus'd us to ſtick and unite cloſer together, may be diſcouraged from all future attempts of this kind, and never be advantag'd through our Diviſions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let us, as well for the honour of our Proteſtant Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and for the credit of our Nation, as to prevent the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God threatened upon us for our Sins, abſtain from all National Sins, and ſuch Crimes as deſerve the ſeverity of Gods Juſtice, and have heretofore involved Kingdoms in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Calamities. Chiefly, let the Miniſters of the Goſpel look carefully to themſelves, and their behaviour, that they may not give occaſion of ſcandal by their Lives. And they whoſe Actions are look'd upon as Examples, ſhould take heed how they countenance thoſe diſorders and Breaches of Gods Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Laws, which his Juſtice hath been oblig'd to puniſh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely in other Nations heretofore.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let ſuch Magiſtrates and Juſtices as are intruſted with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53321:14"/>the execution of the Laws, and his Majeſties Royal Commands, be vigorous, reſolute, and ſpeedy in the performance of their Duties; and aim all their Actions at the publick welfare, the honour of their Prince, the ſafety of Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As their Enemies and ours want not reſolution to put in practice the boldeſt Attempts, methinks our Noble and brave Officers cannot want courage to oppoſe them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Let every one be true, truſty, and faithful in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of thoſe Publick Concerns that are put into our hands; Treachery ſeldom proves faithful and beneficial to the Traytors. It was the Cuſtom of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperour, to hang up a Traytor with the Rewards promiſed for his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: And we all know the Story of that <hi>Roman</hi> Virgin who was killed and buried under the heavy weight of that which was in the Enemies leſt hand; but of all Treaſons, none more dangerous to the Authors, than thoſe which expoſe their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country to the Power and Malice of deſperate and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemies.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Take heed of raiſing or encreaſing the Peoples jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and needleſs fears, by incouraging idle Rumours: It is good to foreſee an approaching danger, for that will prepare us to receive it; but it is dangerous to be too timerous, and ſuſpect a Miſchief where really there is none; and men are commonly diſheartened by flying Tales, which are wont to breed much miſchief in a Government.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Remember your Places, Callings, and Capacities, and act accordingly, without preſuming to meddle with, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe Authority, in matters that are either above our reach, or concern us not immediately.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Let us not be ſparing of our Purſes and Eſtates when the publick ſafety, the honour of our God, the ſafety of our Souls and Religion, the Lives and Fortunes of our Children are in danger; but as our Enemies are ready to ſacrifice their Lives and Fortunes for the promotion of their blind Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and our Ruin, let us expreſs no leſs liberality and genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for our own ſafety, and the defence of our Chriſtian
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53321:14"/>Profeſſion. It is better to give a ſmall Portion of our Eſtates than to loſe all. <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperour, wonder'd at the parcimony of the <hi>Grecians</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> at the tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Imperial City, for though it was full of Plunder and Gold, they choſe rather to ſuffer the <hi>Turks</hi> to carry all away, than to aſſiſt their Emperour with Monies to pay his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented and hired Souldiers. Laſtly, in regard all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, the Prince's vigilancy, and the peoples diſpoſition, are in vain without a bleſſing from the God of Heaven, let us all, by our conſtant and Religious Prayers, ſtrive unanimouſly to obtain it from God; let us beſeech his Divine Goodneſs to watch over us ſtill by his Divine Providence, to diſcover the wicked Machinations of all our bloody Enemies, to defend the perſon and ſacred life of our good King, to grant him a long continuance amongſt us, to direct his Councils, bleſs his Armies, and preſerve our Religion and Government from all future Conſpiracies. If we could be perſwaded to a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful practice of all theſe Advices and Duties, there might be reaſonable hopes of ſecuring our ſelves and Nation from all <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi> We are ſo much the more engaged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; becauſe, not only our gratitude to our Prince calls upon us to joyn with him in promoting our own good, but alſo the ſafety of our Religion is highly concerned; for falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions men have undergone all manner of dangers and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: how much the rather ſhould we take care for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the true Religion; of that Religion which Chriſt and his Apoſtles recommend to us, without which neither we nor our poſterity can reaſonably expect either ſafety or ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; beſides our lives and fortunes are aimed at by theſe <hi>Popiſh Plots.</hi> Thouſands of Families will be utterly undone if they can obtain their ends. No Mercy nor Compaſſion will be ſhewn to ſuch <hi>Hereticks</hi> as they judge us to be. The whole Nation will ſwim in Blood, and we muſt expect all the Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Torments to be exerciſed upon us, that Hell and the Devil can ſuggeſt: and not only our lives will be ſacrificed, but alſo the lives of our Wives, and of our innocent Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53321:15"/>and every where ruine and calamity, miſery and woe, will appear amongſt us, if we ſecure not our ſelves in time. Where is that national Soul which this cannot move and oblige to a timely pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ntion of Popiſh Deſigns of ſuch dreadful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</p>
            <p>In a word, the honour of our God is highly concern'd: To him we owe our Wives, Children, Fortunes, Lives and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; we muſt part with all for the glory of our Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Redeemer: Suffer not this glory to be ſtain'd with Popiſh Superſtitions in this Nation: What a diſhonour will it be, if through our weakneſs, neglect, parcimony, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the <hi>Pope</hi> brings in again into this Land his unſufferable Tyranny, Ignorance, and filthy Abominations.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I pray God ſo to direct his Moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, his Councils and Reſolutions, ſo to proſper his Pious and Religious Endeavours, and ſo to ſtir up all his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the defence of their Laws, Liberties, and Religion, that they may all joyn unanimouſly with him together, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways defeat the proud purpoſes of the <hi>Popiſh Party;</hi> and that none of them may be more wanting to their own good, than his Sacred Majeſty will be to the Safety and Security of the Religion, and Peace of his Kingdoms.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
